Finding Aid for Volney H. Jones Papers 1909-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Biographies and Bibliographies, bulk compiled 1950s-1970s
  - Wildschut, William (Box 4)
  - Will, George F. (Box 4)
  - Willey, Gordon R. (Box 4)
  - Wissler, Clark (Box 4)
  - Witt, Shirley Hill (Box 4)
  - Woodward, Albert Arthur (Box 4)
  - Wyman, Leland C. (Box 4)
  - Yarrow, Harry Crcy (Box 4)
  - Yengoyan, Aram A. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Format (Box 4)
    - List of Contributors to North American Ethnography (Box 4)
    - Sources (Box 4)
- Teaching Files circa 1940s-1960s
  The Teaching Files series, bulk 1940s-1960s (1 linear foot), contains Jones' notes for his popular Aboriginal Cultures of North America course. The files includes Jones' course outlines, lecture notes, resource lists, and information compiled from secondary sources.
  - General
    - Topical Lists
      - 1962 (Box 4)
      - undated (Box 4)
  - Basic Tools and References
    - Anthropological Organizations and Series (Box 4)
    - Reference Volumes (Box 4)
    - Journals, Series and Institutions (Box 4)
  - Tribes and Languages
    - Languages (Box 4)
    - Tribes and Distributions (Box 4)
    - Migrations and Influences (Box 4)
    - Levels of Cultural Development (Box 4)
    - Tribes and Tribal Maps (Box 4)
    - Language Classification (Box 4)
    - Language Reclassification (Box 4)
    - Population (Box 4)
    - Words from Indian Languages (Box 4)
  - Culture Areas and Monographs
    - Concepts and Applications (Box 5)
    - Maps (Box 5)
    - Northern Region (Box 5)
    - Boreal Forest (Box 5)
    - Plains and Prairies (Box 5)
    - Northwest Coast Forest (Box 5)
    - Western (Box 5)
    - Great Basin (Box 5)
    - Central Valley of California (Box 5)
    - Southwest (Box 5)
    - Eastern Woodlands (Box 5)
    - Columbia and Frazer Plateau (Box 5)
  - Technology and Material Culture
    - Textile Industry and Clothing (Box 5)
    - Stone Working (Box 5)
    - Fiber Notes (Box 5)
    - Subsistence (Box 5)
    - "Tobacco" of the Northwest Coast (Box 5)
    - Narcotics and Intoxicants (Box 5)
    - Extractive Processes (Box 5)
    - Water Management (Box 5)
    - Architecture (Box 5)
    - Metal Working (Box 5)
    - Ceramics (Box 5)
    - Arrow Poisons (Box 5)
    - Travel and Transport (Box 5)
    - Fire-Making (Box 5)
    - Fire and Fuels (Box 5)
    - Weapons (Box 5)
    - Implements, Tools and Devices (Box 5)
    - Economics, Land Tenure and Trade (Box 5)
    - Education and Childbearing (Box 5)
    - Law (Box 5)
    - Warfare (Box 5)
    - Social and Political Forms (Box 5)
    - Mescalbean (Box 5)
    - Alcoholic Beverages (Box 5)
    - Tobacco and Smoking (Box 5)
    - Social and Political Forms and Functions (Box 5)
    - Medicine (Box 5)
    - Religious Forms (Box 5)
    - Concept of the Universe (Box 5)
    - Peyote Cult (Box 5)
    - Datura (Jimsosnweed) (Box 5)
    - Contributions (Box 5)
    - Acculturation (Box 5)
    - Legal Status and Administration (Box 5)
    - Physical Type and Racial Affiliations (Box 5)
    - Popular Fallacies (Box 5)
    - Captivities (Box 5)
    - Personalities (Box 5)
    - Musical Bow and Stringed Instruments (Box 5)
    - Literature, Aesthetics and Recreation (Box 5)
    - Ethnoscience (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Culture Areas, compiled 1930s-1960s
  The Culture Areas series, bulk 1930s-1960s (1 linear foot), includes correspondence, notes, reports and citations related to various culture areas, with particular emphasis on plants. Much of the material is undated. While these were primarily reference files, they may have also been compiled in anticipation of authoring a textbook; Jones' order and arrangement of the files has been preserved. In addition to Jones' notes, drafts and outlines, the files include materials written or compiled by others, most notably Jones' mentor at Michigan, Melvin Gilmore. The section on the Plains Region, in particular, includes a number of Gilmore manuscripts and research materials. Jones' thesis on The Ethnobotany of the Isleta Indians can also be found within this series.
  - Desert Shrub Region
    - Arrowweed Gum 1939-1940 (Box 5)
    - Uniola palmeri 1964 (Box 5)
    - Food Plants 1964 (Box 5)
    - Hemenway Expedition-Bibliography 1949 (Box 5)
    - Narcotics and Intoxicants undated (Box 5)
    - Environment undated (Box 5)
    - Anthropology undated (Box 5)
    - Agriculture undated (Box 5)
    - Basin and Plateau Lecture Notes undated (Box 5)
    - Southwest Lecture Notes undated (Box 5)
  - California
    - General (Box 5)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 5)
  - Tundra and Boreal Forest
    - Cree Medicines, Cowie Collection 14043-14060 Specimen Labels (Box 5)
    - Eskimo 1940-1962 (Box 5)
    - Subarctic (Box 5)
    - Subarctic Lecture Notes 1944, undated (Box 5)
    - Arctic Lecture Notes (Box 5)
  - Northwest Coast
    - General (Box 5)
    - Lincoln Totem Pole 1943-1954 (Box 5)
    - West Coast Forest ("Chap. 8") 1934, undated (Box 5)
    - Lecture Notes 1944 (Box 5)
  - Great Lakes Region
    - General (Box 5)
    - Chippewa 1934-1946 (Box 5)
    - Chippewa 1929-1933 (Box 5)
      (notes from Melvin R. Gilmore)
    - Basketry 1948-1969 (Box 5)
    - Basketry-Classification 1933-1934, undated (Box 5)
      (includes photos)
    - Walpole Island (Box 5)
    - Indians of Michigan Bibliography 1966 (Box 5)
    - Plant Materials from Sites in Canada 1931 (Box 5)
      (by Harlan I. Smith)
    - Hiawatha (Box 5)
    - Jesuit Relations (Box 5)
    - Textiles (report of field work) 1933 (Box 5)
    - Pottawattami Indians 1926 (Box 5)
      (notes from Gilmore)
    - Wild Rice (Box 5)
    - Iroquois Basketry 1946 (Box 5)
    - Textile Arts 1933-1963 (Box 5)
    - Lake Forest and Deciduous Forest ("Chap. 9") (Box 5)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 5)
    - Tobacco and Smoking (Box 5)
  - Plains Region
    - General (Box 6)
    - Painted Bison Robe-Witthoft (Box 6)
    - The Mandan (Box 6)
      (notes from Edward S. Curtis by Gilmore)
    - Osage Information 1925-1954 (Box 6)
      (from Gilmore)
    - Pawnee Data 1914-1926 (Box 6)
    - Silphium 1931 (Box 6)
    - Temperate Grasslands ("Chap. 10") (Box 6)
    - Plant Specimens from Montana 1925 (Box 6)
    - Ground Bean and Its Uses (Box 6)
    - Ethnography (Box 6)
    - Santee Prescriptions-Frazier (Box 6)
    - Medicinal Plants of Nebraska 1909 (Box 6)
    - The Pasque Flower in Indian Lore (Box 6)
    - Nebraska Plants (Box 6)
    - North Dakota Flora (Box 6)
    - Polystictus Versicolor as a Food Plant 1912 (Box 6)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 6)
    - Ethnobotany of the Chippewa 1937 (Box 6)
      (by Gretchen Beardsley)
  - Eastern Woodlands
    - Cherokee Alphabet 1944 (Box 6)
    - Bibliography of Kentucky Botany (Box 6)
      (by H.T. Shacklette)
    - Deciduous Forest 1927, undated (Box 6)
    - Southeast 1933, undated (Box 6)
    - Plant Remains from the Baum Village Site (Box 6)
      (notes on publication by W. C. Mills)
    - Sassafras 1948 (Box 6)
    - Adena and Hopewell Carbon 14 Dates circa 1950 (Box 6)
      (by James B. Griffin)
    - Prehistoric Pottery of the Eastern United States 1950-1952 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Mexico and Tropics
    - Tropics ("Chap. 13") (Box 6)
    - Huasteca (Box 6)
    - Mescalbeans 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - The Vegetable World of the Ancient Peruvians 1940 (Box 6)
      (translation of article by Yakovleff and Herrera)
    - Chihuahua Textiles 1940-1949 (Box 6)
    - Cultural Evolution as a Guide to Conquest Situations in South America 1963 (Box 6)
      (by Sam Vinocur)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Southwest and Great Basin
    - General 1931-1933 (Box 6)
    - Guayave (Box 6)
    - Navajo Dyes 1957 (Box 6)
    - Garryowen 1953 (Box 6)
    - Alfalfa 1937 (Box 6)
    - New Mexico History Bibliography (Box 6)
    - Bird Whistles Among Pueblos (Box 6)
    - Southwest and New Mexico ("Chapter 12") (Box 6)
    - Fauna and Flora of New Mexico Bibliography 1930-1931 (Box 6)
    - The Ethnobotany of the Islet Indians, 1931 (Thesis) (Box 6)
    - Uses of Vegetal Pigments in Southwestern Pottery Paints (Box 6)
    - Fibers from Montezuma Castle 1938-1939 (Box 6)
- Ethnobotany Textbook Files, compiled circa 1945-1978
  The Ethnobotany Textbook Files series, ca. 1945-1978 (0.75 linear feet), includes outlines, notes, drafts, and correspondence Jones compiled for a planned textbook on ethnobotany that he worked on from approximately 1945 to 1978 but never completed. Much of the material is undated. While a complete outline for the book is not found in the papers, Jones' order and arrangement of the files has been preserved to give a sense of the book's intended organization. As with the Culture Areas series, the files include material written or compiled by others, as well as by Jones.
  - Chapter 2-Interrelations of Man and Environment
    - Outline (Box 6)
    - Floral Environment and Its Influence (Box 6)
    - Exploitation of Flora (Box 6)
    - Plant Needs and Plant Wants (Box 6)
    - Basic Dependence of Man on Plants (Box 6)
  - Chapter 3-Indian and His Environment
    - Flora of Archaeological Sites (Box 6)
    - Human Ecology-Man and Nature (Box 6)
    - Regions and Areas of North America (Box 6)
    - Nature and Origin of American Indian (Box 6)
    - Sources for Relation of Nature to Aboriginal Man (Box 6)
  - Chapter 4-Agriculture
    - New World as Independent Center of Domestication (Box 6)
    - Nature of American Agricultural Pattern (Box 6)
    - Evidence on Origin and Diffusion of American Agriculture (Box 6)
    - Significance of New World Agriculture (Box 6)
    - Distribution and Patterns of Agriculture in North America (Box 6)
  - Chapter 14-Foods
    - Outline (Box 6)
    - Camas and the Flathead Indians of Montana (Box 6)
      (by Richard Malouf)
    - Crayfish in Haiti (Box 6)
    - Archaeological Chenopodium (Box 6)
    - Nelumbo lutea and Waterlillies as Food (Box 6)
    - Subsistence and Foods (Box 6)
    - Food Requirements of Man (Box 6)
    - Patterns of Food Preservation (Box 6)
    - All American Menus (Box 6)
    - Food and Diet (Box 6)
    - Origin and Sources of Food (Box 6)
    - Nature and Availability of Nutrients (Box 6)
    - Utilization of Food (Box 6)
    - Influence and Importance of Food Supply (Box 6)
    - Food Plants (Box 6)
    - Celtis (from Gilmore) (Box 6)
    - Parallelism of Food Plants (Box 6)
      (by J.V.A. Drummond)
    - Paraguay Tea (Box 6)
    - Archaeological Starch (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Chapter 15-Technology and Arts
    - General (Box 7)
    - Rubber Balls and Rubber Sources (Box 7)
    - Cryptostegia Rubber (Box 7)
    - Touchwood (Box 7)
    - Gums, Resins, Pigments, etc. (Box 7)
    - Apocynum (Box 7)
    - Plants in Pottery Manufacture (Box 7)
    - Japanese Fishing Floats (Box 7)
    - Cordage (Box 7)
    - Clothing and Ornament (Box 7)
    - Plant Technology (Box 7)
    - Vegetable Fibers (Box 7)
  - Medicine
    - Bones as Medicine (Box 7)
    - Allionia as Medicine (Box 7)
    - Drugs of the North American Indian (Box 7)
  - Chapter 17-Narcotics, Intoxicants, Poisons
    - General (Box 7)
    - Nicotiana (Box 7)
    - Smoking of Mullein (Box 7)
    - Mexico-Toxic Euphorbiceae, Sapium, Sebastiana, Croton, etc. (Box 7)
    - Fish Poisons (Box 7)
  - Chapter 19-Non-Utilitarian Aspects
    - General (Box 7)
    - Phenology (Box 7)
    - Chemical, Social, Psychological (Box 7)
  - Chapter 20-Influence of Man on Plants
    - Outline (Box 7)
    - Maintenance of Prairie Conditions, Fire and Burning of Areas (Box 7)
    - Juglans hindsii (Box 7)
    - Phytogeography (Box 7)
    - Domestication and Its Influence (Box 7)
    - Mode of Action (Box 7)
    - Indian as a Factor in Plant Ecology (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Mosses as Economic Plants (Box 7)
    - Lichens (Box 7)
    - "Industrial Revolutions: Plants, Animals and Metals" (talk for WUOM radio) 1950 (Box 7)
    - Cultural Ecology (Box 7)
    - American Museum of Natural History (Box 7)
    - Archaeological Algae (Box 7)
    - Fremont Expedition (Box 7)
    - Indians Taken to Europe (Box 7)
    - Economy of North American Indians (Box 7)
    - Survey of American Indian Botany (Box 7)
    - Economic Plants Family Tree (Box 7)
- Hopi Research Files
  The Hopi Research Files series, ca. 1946 -- 1979, (0.5 linear feet) contains Volney Jones' correspondence, notes, and drafts on the history of Hopi reservations, their agents and administration, and expeditions to the Hopi people. A few photographs are included with the material.
  - Tusayan; History of the Hopi Reservation 1850-1868, circa 1973, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Tusayan; History of the Hopi Reservation 1869-1881, circa 1973 (Box 7)
  - Tusayan; History of the Hopi Reservation 1882-1890, circa 1973 (Box 7)
  - Tusayan; Outline for the History of. undated (Box 7)
  - The Hopi Reservation After 1860 undated (Box 7)
  - Colyer and Palmer expedition to the Hopi Indians 1869, 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - The Shimono Indians circa 1969 (Box 7)
  - Asa Gray's Journey into the GrandCanyon in 1885, circa 1971 (Box 7)
  - Thomas Keam; Government Agent to the Hopi Indians circa 1946-1950 (includes photos) (Box 7)
  - Hopi Snake Dance 1879-1891, undated (Box 7)
- Maize Research
  The Maize Research series, ca. 1950s -- 1978 (.1 linear feet) contains notes, drafts and publications about Jones' research on maize. The original arrangement of the research notes has been preserved
  - Notes & Drafts (Box 8)
  - Notes & Drafts
    - Mangelsdorf and carrer & the book (Box 8)
    - Mangelsdorf and Reeves collaboration 1927-1959 (Box 8)
    - Tribe Maydeae closer kin (Box 8)
    - Tripartite hypothesis (Box 8)
    - Implication of hypothesis Theories of origin (Box 8)
    - Teosinte in anthropology Spinden & others (Box 8)
    - Reactions -- botanical and anthropological (Box 8)
    - Wild corn and pollen (Box 8)
    - Popcorn and podcorn (Box 8)
    - Teosinte as hybrid (Box 8)
    - Tripsacoid concept (Box 8)
    - Races, lineages, evolutionary sequence -- multiple (Box 8)
    - Bat cave (Box 8)
    - Tamaulipas (Box 8)
    - Tehuacan (Box 8)
    - Northwest Mexico and Southwest (Box 8)
    - Euphoria and overtaken (Box 8)
    - Present status and needs (Box 8)
    - M's present position (Box 8)
    - Assessment of interpretations -- procedure? (Box 8)
    - Abstracts (Box 8)
    - Outline (Box 8)
  - Publications (Box 8)
- Teaching Files circa 1940s-1960s (cont.)
  - Anthropology 101 Files
    - Files I -- Americas as of 1492 (Box 8)
    - Files II-Post 1492 (Box 8)
    - Files III-Topical (Box 8)
  - Anthro 320 -- Primitive Technology (Box 8)
  - Anthro 557 Aboriginal Cultures, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Ethnobotany of the Indians of North America-bibliography (Box 8)
Related Material
Additional biographical information about Volney Jones may be found in The Nature and Status of Ethnobotany, edited by Richard I. Ford, University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology Anthropological Papers no. 67, and "Volney Hurt Jones, 1930-1982" by C. Wesley Cowan, American Antiquity 53(3), 1988, pages 455-460.
For further information about the Ethnobotanical Laboratory, see "The Ethnobotanical Laboratory at the University of Michigan" by Melvin R. Gilmore, published as University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology Occasional Contributions, no. 1, as well as the Melvin R. Gilmore Papers, available at the Bentley Library.